In computer science and information theory, a Huffman code is a particular type of optimal
prefix code that is commonly used for lossless data compression. The process of finding or
using such a code is Huffman coding, an algorithm developed by David A. Huffman while he
was a Sc.D. student at MIT, and published in the 1952 paper "A Method for the Construction
of Minimum-Redundancy Codes".[1]

The output from Huffman's algorithm can be viewed as a variable-length code table for
encoding a source symbol (such as a character in a file). The algorithm derives this table
from the estimated probability or frequency of occurrence (weight) for each possible value
of the source symbol. As in other entropy encoding methods, more common symbols are
generally represented using fewer bits than less common symbols. Huffman's method can be
efficiently implemented, finding a code in time linear to the number of input weights if
these weights are sorted.[2] However, although optimal among methods encoding symbols
separately, Huffman coding is not always optimal among all compression methods - it is
replaced with arithmetic coding[3] or asymmetric numeral systems[4] if a better
compression ratio is required.